Finding Aid for the Helen Matthewson Club. Subject files. 1933-1987.
UCLA Library Special Collections
Helen Matthewson Club. Subject files.
1933-1987
University Archives Record Series 446
UCLA Library Special Collections
0.8 linear ft. (2 boxes)
Record Series 446 contains the subject files of the Helen Matthewson Club (HMC) and alumnae.
Helen Matthewson Club. 1923-1965
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Historical Note
The Helen Matthewson Club (HMC) was established in the fall of 1923 by Dean of Women Helen Matthewson Laughlin as a living cooperative where self supporting University women could enjoy the companionship of others, obtain adequate housing at a fair price, and serve the school and community. The HMC was initially located at Oakwood House near the Vermont Ave. campus of the University of California Southern Branch [UCLA]. With the Fall 1929 opening of UCLA's Westwood campus, the HMC relocated to a new home at 900 Hilgard Ave.
On June 30, 1950 the HMC house at 900 Hilgard Ave. was "dissolved" and the property used for a new UCLA religious center. With the help of the Helen Matthewson Club Alumnae (HMCA) the remaining HMC active members joined the Phenix Club in Santa Monica. In 1954 the Phenix Club formally merged with the HMC. In 1957 the HMC acquired a house at 820 Levering Ave. As a result of decreasing membership, the Levering Ave. house closed in 1965. In the same year, 1965, the Helen Matthewson Memorial Scholarship fund was established and administered by the HMCA.
Helen Matthewson Laughlin (b.1881-d.1960) served as the Los Angeles State Normal School Dean of Women (1911-1919) and the UCLA Dean of Women (1919-1946).
Scope and Content
Record Series 446 contains the subject files of the Helen Matthewson Club (HMC) and alumnae. Files include articles of incorporation, by-laws, financial documents, events, and scholarship files, as well as information on Laughlin Residential Suites and the HMC residence on Levering Ave.
Acronyms and initialisms appearing in this series include:
HMC = Helen Matthewson Club
HMCA = Helen Matthewson Club Alumnae
This is an inactive record series; no additional University records are expected to be added.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 1720433
- Annual HMC Breakfast - invitations., 1971-1973. (Box 1)
- Annual HMC Breakfast - programs., 1940-1979.; 4 folders (Box 1)
- Articles of incorporation and by-laws., 1939-1967. (Box 1)
- Financial documents., 1961-1968. (Box 1)
- Annual HMC Breakfast - programs., 1980-1987. (Box 2)
- Annual HMC Breakfast - programs for Tenth (10th) and Twenty-fifth (25th) anniversaries., 1934; 1949. (Box 2)
- Guest book., 1933-1956. (Box 2)
- Laughlin Residential Suites., 1949-1981. (Box 2)
- Levering House., 1958-1959. (Box 2)
- Scholarship., 1950-1986. (Box 2)
- Song book. "H.M.C. Songs.", n.d. (Box 2)
- UCLA Magazine. "Helen Matthewson Laughlin.", 1940 Apr. (Box 2)